<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://yihao001.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://yihao001.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-07-06T18:09:39+00:00</updated><id>https://yihao001.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Revamp</title><link href="https://yihao001.github.io/blog/2024/revamp/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Revamp"/><published>2024-07-03T13:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-03T13:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://yihao001.github.io/blog/2024/revamp</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yihao001.github.io/blog/2024/revamp/"><![CDATA[<p>hi!</p> <p>I’ve finally switched to a new layout with dark mode and the website is now so much easier on the eyes.</p> <p>This is so much more flexible and it even has distil-like posts which I’ll definitely use some time in the future.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="non-acad"/><category term="aside"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[refresh!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Confusion Matrices in sklearn</title><link href="https://yihao001.github.io/blog/2020/confusion/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Confusion Matrices in sklearn"/><published>2020-05-21T16:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-21T16:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yihao001.github.io/blog/2020/confusion</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yihao001.github.io/blog/2020/confusion/"><![CDATA[<p>The confusion_matrix function in sklearn is useful but the documentation can be confusing.</p> <p>Assuming that you’re using integer labels (i.e. 0 or 1), one’d think that True Positive will be on the top left corner, but it’s on the diagonally opposite end instead!</p> <p>The official documentation doesn’t directly provide 2 critical pieces of information:</p> <ol> <li>A figure would’ve helped, so here it is (for binary classification):</li> </ol> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/confusion_matrix-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/confusion_matrix-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/confusion_matrix-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/confusion_matrix.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <ol> <li> <p>What is considered positive or negative by default? (i.e. without feeding in the ‘labels’ param)</p> <p>0 is assumed to be negative (N), 1 is thus positive (P)</p> </li> </ol> <p>If your labels are strings, the above <strong>does not always apply</strong>. Instead, sklearn will follow the <strong>alphabetical order</strong> of the labels: e.g. if the labels are ‘Alice’ and ‘Bob’, [0,0] is the number of instances where prediction == ground truth == ‘Alice’. [0,1], i.e. top right cell, is the number of times ‘Bob’ was predicted but ground truth is ‘Alice’.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="acad"/><category term="ml"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[confusion matrices are confusing]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Learning Machines</title><link href="https://yihao001.github.io/blog/2020/learning/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Learning Machines"/><published>2020-03-21T16:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-03-21T16:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yihao001.github.io/blog/2020/learning</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yihao001.github.io/blog/2020/learning/"><![CDATA[<p>Attended <a href="https://twitter.com/NTUsg/status/1215818307460157440">a sharing session by GIC’s CEO</a> and even though it’s a part of a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Adaptive Skills 4.0 Speaker Series</code> and sounds only tangentially related to research / academia, it helped to give some structure to the work I’m doing.</p> <p>3 key takeaways (based on my own interpretation):</p> <ol> <li> <p>Being a learning machine</p> <p>It’s always good to have condensed and pre-processed information, like how a country’s leaders can get the best specialists in the area to explain to them about concept they might not know. Most of us aren’t world leaders (yet, haha!), but we can similarly maintain a good cache / database of past knowledge (that’s quickly and easily retrievable) + know people in adjacent fields who we can consult (and of course, you should help them out too). Most importantly, be in a constant process of learning (observe, think, express/apply) - in other words, don’t just be a database. Act on the information you have.</p> </li> <li> <p>Problem stages: Business vs Engineering vs Science</p> <p>In academia, we’re mostly working on ‘Science’ problems and we’re in the business of creating new technology. When the ‘Science’ problems are solved / proven to be possible, then it’s a matter of engineering the right solution. Finally, if / when the engineering problems are addressed, it doesn’t mean that it will lead to a viable business. Perhaps the engineering problem is solved, but the product might not be at a viable cost that consumers are willing to pay a premium over it.</p> <p>E.g. Selling a bicycle: someone had to figure out the physics of how a bicycle can operate (e.g. friction between wheels and ground, circular motion, torque); then comes the engineering problem (e.g. aerodynamics) ; then it’s a matter of developing a business model that can ensure sustainability of the business (e.g. cost management, procurement, marketing)</p> <p>All companies in all industries are in some stage of this process. Some industries are not yet at the business stage, or even the engineering stage (e.g. fMRI). Blockchain is an area where lots of work is still going on in terms of engineering (the science problem is solved to an extent, but some people have tried to rush the business side of things too - that’s possibly why we see the crazy swings it has when more people realize that some of the security issues are not ironed out yet!</p> <p>Be in time for the future - not too early.</p> </li> <li> <p>Investing in such a turbulent environment</p> <ul> <li>Besides think about what to change, what do you not change? Some organisations have to stick to principles, even in crisis.</li> <li>Diversification is still the only free lunch, but you need more than it to do better</li> <li>Take risks that you understand + you’re compensated appropriately</li> </ul> </li> </ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="non-acad"/><category term="aside"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[beyond machine learning]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Decomposing huge matrices</title><link href="https://yihao001.github.io/blog/2020/decompose/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Decomposing huge matrices"/><published>2020-01-09T16:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-01-09T16:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yihao001.github.io/blog/2020/decompose</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yihao001.github.io/blog/2020/decompose/"><![CDATA[<p>In fMRI analyses, a common approach is to use a correlation matrix to study the relationships between various brain regions. Brain parcellations schemes seem to be getting finer over the years and that will increase with more detailed parcellation schemes proposed / better imaging resolution - that means there might be more and more regions.</p> <p>One such atlas is from Power et al., which gives 264 regions of interest. A 264 x 264 correlation matrix gives 34716 unique features (correlation between the time series of each pair of nodes). If you want to study the correlation between these edge features (across subjects) - that’s going to become a 34716 x 34716 matrix!</p> <p>Processing it is going to be a pain. There are some tricks mentioned below, but it is still a pain (in terms of time + memory consumption).</p> <ol> <li>Store and load it using hdf5 via <a href="http://docs.h5py.org/en/stable/quick.html">h5py</a>.</li> <li>If it’s sparse, there are <a href="https://docs.scipy.org/doc/scipy/reference/sparse.linalg.html">many ways to speed it up</a>, e.g. <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">scipy.sparse.linalg.eigs(h)</code></li> <li>If it’s approximately sparse (many very small values), make it sparse (e.g. set small correlation values to 0). You’ll lose info, so you’d need to weigh the cost/benefits</li> <li>Do you really need all the eigenvalues? If not (e.g. only need the largest few or smallest few), Lanczos algorithm gives a <a href="https://scicomp.stackexchange.com/questions/23536/quality-of-eigenvalue-approximation-in-lanczos-method">much faster approximation of the tails</a>.</li> </ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="acad"/><category term="fmri"/><category term="networks"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In fMRI analyses, a common approach is to use a correlation matrix to study the relationships between various brain regions. Brain parcellations schemes seem to be getting finer over the years and that will increase with more detailed parcellation schemes proposed / better imaging resolution - that means there might be more and more regions.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Repurposing hard disks</title><link href="https://yihao001.github.io/blog/2019/repurpose/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Repurposing hard disks"/><published>2019-10-12T16:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-10-12T16:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yihao001.github.io/blog/2019/repurpose</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yihao001.github.io/blog/2019/repurpose/"><![CDATA[<p>tl;dr: If your desktop / laptop breaks down, it doesn’t always mean that everything is broken (it’s usually because of 1 critical component). Out of all the components, one of the useful parts that can still be used (without going through too much trouble) is your <strong>internal</strong> hard disk. You can repurpose it with a few tweaks and get additional storage space!</p> <p>Caveats: Some laptops aren’t easy to disassemble and will require <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Torx">special screwdrivers</a> but most of them are easy. Money spent to buy these equipments &lt; value you will unlock by reusing parts that still work. :) <br/><br/></p> <hr/> <p><br/></p> <h3 id="backstory">Backstory</h3> <p>Recently, my all-in-one desktop had issues with starting up and I accidentally killed the hard disk by switching off the power while it was booting up… it just crashes every time it tries to start (I’m guessing the disk got scratched and some parts that were essential for the booting process got corrupted - a few of my files were corrupted too) but luckily I could still access the command prompt in the Windows Recovery Environment. But <a href="https://support.microsoft.com/en-us/help/323007/how-to-copy-a-folder-to-another-folder-and-retain-its-permissions">transferring files from a hard disk to another via the command prompt (with the xcopy command) was a huge pain</a> especialy when my hard disk was bigger than my external HDD, had to transfer things to and fro another laptop multiple times.</p> <p>So I got a <a href="https://www.courts.com.sg/samsung-mz-76e500bw-2-5in-860-evo-500gb-ssd-internal-ssd-ip137598">new SSD (an affordable Samsung EVO860 500GB)</a> and got it set up pretty quickly and the desktop revived. Guess the hypothesis was quite correct.</p> <h3 id="main-content">Main content</h3> <p>I have a habit of disassembling my old/spoilt computers and sending everything except the hard disk for recycling. So this incident made me realise that they could be repurposed as an external HDD - but it took more time than expected. I did quite a lot of reading up, but still ended up buying the wrong things. But with the following information gathered from this experience, repurposing is actually as simple as:</p> <ol> <li>Disassembling your computer</li> <li>Getting the correct SATA-USB cable</li> <li>Plugging it into another computer just like what you do with a portable HDD</li> </ol> <h3 id="essential-background-knowledge">Essential background knowledge</h3> <ol> <li> <p>IDE/PATA vs SATA</p> <p>I had a range of hard disks (made in 2006, ~2012, 2016) and the 2006 was an 80GB one (from an ancient NEC laptop!)</p> <p>Here’s how to <a href="https://www.reclaime.com/library/how-to-tell-ide-from-sata.aspx">differentiate between them</a>, basically SATA has a flatter connector while IDE has 2 rows of wire ends. The latter is much older (it’s the 2006 one for mine!)</p> <p>There are 2 types of SATA: 2.5 inch and 3.5 inch, the latter is generally older than the former (and mine was both 2.5 inch HDDs).</p> </li> <li> <p>Enclosure or Cable?</p> <p>Many websites recommended <a href="https://www.howtogeek.com/268249/how-to-turn-an-old-hard-drive-into-an-external-drive/">buying an enclosure</a> but I wasn’t a fan of that idea. Instead, I bought the <a href="https://www.qoo10.sg/item/USB-3-0-TO-2-5-INCH-SATA-CABLE-CONVERTER-ADAPTER-HARD-DISK-6/603602163?banner_no=1305330">cheapest (but still legitimate looking) SATA to USB cable I’ve found</a> and it does light up but the hard disk doesn’t get recognised by the computer (and the hard disk isn’t spinning at all). Naturally, all the debugging didn’t work.</p> <p>On hindsight, I should’ve spent a few more dollars to get one with <a href="https://superuser.com/questions/1372617/can-a-sata-to-usb-cable-run-a-sata-hard-disk-off-a-usb-port">extra power supply</a>. Got one from <a href="https://www.lazada.sg/products/free-uk-power-adapterugreen-sata-to-usb-adapter-usb-30-20-cable-to-sata-converter-for-samsung-seagate-wd-25-35-hdd-ssd-hard-disk-usb-sata-adapter-uk-plug-intl-i6393383-s8040426.html">here</a> and it generally worked well. So you don’t really need an enclosure after all (if you’re okay with leaving the hard disk in the open - just remember to keep it in an airy place, wipe it when it’s dusty, or just use it only when you need to).</p> </li> </ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="non-acad"/><category term="tech"/><category term="green"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[many parts of a crashed computer are still reusable]]></summary></entry></feed>